A Guide to the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Administrative Functions, RG 4 FA1798
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation records, Administrative Functions, RG 4
1943-2019
Rockefeller Archive Center
John S. and James L. Knight Foundation
FA1798
33.0 Cubic Feet (87 containers)
Conditions Governing Access
Records more than 10 years old are open for research with select materials restricted as noted. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC. Researchers interested in accessing digital media (floppy disks, CDs, DVDs, etc.) in this collection must use an access surrogate. The original items may not be accessed because of preservation concerns. To request an access surrogate be made, or if you are unsure if there is an access surrogate, please contact an archivist.
Scope and Contents
Record Group 4, Administrative Functions, is comprised of the records of the Finance, Human Resources and Communications areas. A complete chronicle of the Foundation's finances is contained in the federal tax returns (Form 990s). This record group holds tax returns for the years 1952 to 2018. Human Resources materials include Policy and Procedures Manuals, Benefits and Compensation Plans, and Strategic Planning files. The Communications files offer insights into the public perception of Knight Foundation, through its collection of news releases about Foundation activities, publications, special events, and biographical records of prominent figures in its history.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged as follows:
Subgroup 1: Administration, 1983-2019
Subgroup 2: Communications, 1943-2017
Subgroup 3: Finance, 1950-2019
- Administration, 1983-2019; 1; 3.42 Cubic Feet 8 letter document boxes and 2 half-letter document boxes
  - Archives & Records Management, 1996-2016; 1.1; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    Scope and Contents
    These files contain a proposal for an Archives and Records Management Program by The Winthrop Group, archives project correspondence, a file and archives chronological log, draft and final versions of the Document Management Manual, and revised records schedules.
    - Winthrop Group Proposal for Archives and Records Management Program, 1996 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 1)
      General
      Knight File Number - 1089
      Proposal by the Winthrop Group to create an archives and records management program for KF: "Documenting the Past, Preparing for the Future: Archives and Records Management at the John S. and James L. Knight Foundation."
    - Project Correspondence, 1996 September 1-December 1 (Box 1, Folder 2)
      Knight File Number - 1090
      Memos, correspondence, and e-mails re: establishment of an archives and records management program, including the work done by the Winthrop Group.
    - File and Archive Chronological Log, 1997 Febuary 27-August 14 (Box 1, Folder 3-4)
      Knight File Number - 2107
      This chronological log documents the work of the task force on the records/archives project. It includes reports, meeting minutes, action items, and decisions. Also included is a decision flow process chart.
    - Procedures Manual for Documentation Management, 1997 September 1-December 1 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
      Knight File Number - 1091
      Procedures manual with records policy, retention schedules (master), information about the Archives program (collecting policy, access policy, accession form, etc. Two folders. Second folder contain draft manual prepared by archives consultants (The Winthrop Group, Inc.).
    - Records Retention Schedule, 1998 January 1 (Box 1, Folder 7)
      Knight File Number - 2878
      Lists Department, Retention and Final Disposition. This is the first version submitted by Winthrop Group in July 1997, with revisions by Knight Foundation, effective January 1, 1998.
    - Records Retention Schedule (revised), 2002 June 25 (Box 1, Folder 8)
      Knight File Number - 2108
      Lists Department, Retention and Final Disposition. Record copy with original signatures
    - Records Retention Schedule (revised) 2016, 2015-2016 (Box 1, Folder 9)
      Knight File Number - 5914
      Lists Department, Retention and Final Disposition. Record copy with some original signatures for 2015 changes.
  - Corporate Art, 1990-2017; 1.2; 0.38 Cubic Feet 1 letter document box
    Contains correspondence and inventories pertaining to the purchase and value of art and artifacts for the Miami office of the Knight Foundation.
    - Correspondence and Inventories, 1990 September 4-1993 May 4 (Box 1, Folder 10)
      Knight File Number - 2109
      Correspondence and inventories concerning the purchase and value of art and artifacts for the Miami offices of the Knight Foundation.
    - Art Work Project, 1998 November 11-2017 April 11 (Box 1, Folder 11)
      Knight File Number - 2881
      Correspondence and invoices concerning the purchase of art for the Miami offices of the Knight Foundation. Clara Knight portrait commission, John B. Martin, artist.
  - Human Resources, 1983-2017; 1.3; 2.28 Cubic Feet 5 letter document boxes and 2 half-letter document boxes
    Arrangement
    Arranged first by subseries (Administrative Files, Benefits, Policies, Staffing, and Strategic Planning) then chronologically.
    The files include documents on employee benefits, such as vision plans, 403(b) plans, long-term disability, retirement plans, and the matching gift program. Often several updated versions are included. Several versions of the Knight Foundation's Personnel and Policy Manuals (1983-2002), along with files on the candidate selection process also are included. In addition, information exists on new employee orientation (2003), staff streamlining (1998-1999) and strategic planning (1999).
    - Benefits, 1983-2016; 3.1
      - Retirement Plan - Actuarial Report for Plan Year 1988, 1988 November 30 (Box 1, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 2631
        The actuarial report indicates the pension expense and the minimum required contribution for 1988, provides a review of the funded status of the plan and compares actual and expected experience under the plan during 1987. Also includes a description of the Retirement Plan for Employees of the Knight Foundation as of 1988.
      - Deferred Compensation Plan Participants, 1994 May 1-1995 September 26 (Box 1, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 2114
        Includes a revised version of the Knight Foundation Deferred Compensation Plan, correspondence re: an IRS ruling, and a plan amendment and restatement.
      - Employer Administration Manual, 1996-1998 (Box 1, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 2115
        Prepared for the Knight Foundation by MetLife, it is designed to assist KF in maintaining its records and administering the Plan benefits.
      - 403(b) Plan (Defined Contribution Pension Plan), 1991-2002 (Box 1, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 2110
        Includes text, summaries, revisions and amendments to the Section 403(b) plan, which allows for a deferral of up to 25% of an employee's compensation to be distributed after retirement.
      - 403(b) Plan (Defined Contribution Pension Plan), 1992-1997 (Box 1, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 2111
        Correspondence and IRS filings re: Knight's Section 403(b) plan, which allows for a deferral of up to 25% of an employee's compensation to be distributed after retirement.
      - Matching Gifts Program, 1997-2014 (Box 1, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 2119
        Conditions Governing Access
        Restricted - Open 2025
        Memo from Belinda Lawrence to Knight Foundation Trustees re: the Knight Foundation matching gifts program, which matches trustee and employee gifts to non-profit organizations on a 2 for 1 basis up to $5,000 per year. Also included is a blank matching gift donor/recipient form. Also included are memos from Maria Yero, grants associate, and Bahia Ramos, Community Foundations, reminding employees of the benefit.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of the Knight Foundation, 1989-1997 (Box 1, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 2120
        Description of the Retirement Plan for Employees of the Knight Foundation, as revised in 1989. Also includes several other later revisions and amendments and a summary plan description.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of Knight Foundation - First Amendment, 1992 October 30 (Box 1, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 2121
        First Amendment to the Retirement Plan for Employees of Knight Foundation of January 1, 1989.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of Knight Foundation - Summary Plan Descriptions, 1989-1999 (Box 1, Folder 9)
        Knight File Number - 2122
        Summary Plan Descriptions for the Retirement Plan for Employees of the Knight Foundation.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of Knight Foundation - Correspondence, 1989 September 5-July 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 2124
        Correspondence refers to proposed changes in eligibility requirements, amendments to the retirement plan, appointment of an administrative committee, and IRS rulings.
      - Employee Benefits: Health, Life Insurance, Accident Benefits, 1997 March 10-1998 March 9 (Box 1, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 1136
        Knight Foundation Employee Benefits Plan for plan year 3/10/97-3/9/98. Includes Health Benefits, Life Insurance and Accident Benefits, Summary Plan Description, Florida State Amendments, and Master Policies.
      - Comprehensive Employee Statements, 1996 March 5 (Box 1, Folder 12)
        Knight File Number - 2112
        Provides total payroll and benefits paid out to employees in 1995.
      - Defined Benefit Plan - IRS Form 5500, 1997 July 31 (Box 1, Folder 13)
        Knight File Number - 2113
        Completed IRS Form 5500-C/R "Return/Report of Employee Benefit Plan" for 1996 re: retirement plan for employees of Knight Foundation.
      - Long Term Disability Plan, 1997 January 10 (Box 1, Folder 14)
        Knight File Number - 2118
        Contract for the Long Term Disability coverage effective March 10, 1996 between Knight Foundation and its insurance carrier, MetLife.
      - Group Life and AD&D Insurance Plan, 1998 June 1 (Box 1, Folder 15)
        Knight File Number - 2117
        Manual, prepared by Metlife for Knight Foundation employees, describing the benefits in its Group Life and Accidental Death and Dismemberment Benefits plan.
      - Flexible Benefit Plan, 1997-1999 (Box 1, Folder 16)
        Knight File Number - 2116
        Plan and election of benefits form for the Knight Foundation flexible benefit plan, which allows employees to choose among different types of benefits. Payroll deductions may be excludable from employees' incomes.
      - Vision Service Plan, 1999 March (Box 1, Folder 17)
        Knight File Number - 2127
        Benefit outline and brochure describing the vision service plan benefit for Knight employees.
      - Summary of Employee Benefits, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 18)
        Knight File Number - 2126
        1999 Summary of Employee Benefits is an employee manual which explains the benefits availble to Knight Foundation employees.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of Knight Foundation - Actuarial Valuation Report, 2000 May (Box 2, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 2125
        May 2000 Actuarial Valuation Report for the retirement plan for employees of the Knight Foundation prepared by William M. Mercer, Inc. presents the results of their review and provides reportiing and disclosure information for financial statements, governmental agencies and other interested parties.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of the Knight Foundation Form 5300, 2000-2009 March (Box 2, Folder 2-3)
        Knight File Number - 4204
        Materials submitted to the IRS for determination of Knight Foundation's Employee Benefit Plan include: copy of proposed amendment and restatement along with executed copies of the prior plan document and all amendments thereto; copy of proposed 5th amendment required by the IRS as part of the still pending GUST submission; copy of employee notification regarding submission of the Plan to the IRS for a determination; completed form 5300 and all required attachments; copy of the plan's prior determination letter and all amendments and plan restatements; and form 2848. Also included are letters from the IRS acknowledging receipt of the request and providing a document locator number and, finally, a favorable determination of the plan. Also included is additional correspondence between the IRS and Mercer re: favorable determination of the retirement plan, dating 2008/2009 and a copy of a Board resolution (dated March 9. 2009) approving the retirement plan for employees of Knight Foundation. (2 folders)
      - Employee Benefit Plan - IRS Form 5500, 2001 December 31 (Box 2, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 2378
        Amended Annual Return/Report of Employee Benefit Plan for the year ended 12/31/2001, IRS Form 5500. Contains some hand-written notes. NOTE: Contents discovered to be missing 4/30/2007 by LCP.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of the Knight Foundation, 2003 April (Box 2, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 4076
        Includes Actuarial Valuation Report as of 1/1/2003 for the plan year and fiscal year ending 12/31/2003, including FAS 87 expense for the fiscal year ending 12/31/2003.
      - Vanguard Recordkeeping Fee Agreement, 2008 December (Box 2, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 4430
        The fee is for administering the employee benefit plan.
      - 403(b) Retirement Plan for Employees of Knight Foundation, Amended and Restated; 2008 AFTAP Certific, 1996 December 18-2012 August 27 (Box 2, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 4387
        Knight Foundation Section 403(b) Plan, Amended and Restated as of June 1, 2008 includes definitions, participation, contributions, vesting, investment options, distributions, administration, and signatures and five amendments to the 403B plan. Also included is a memo from Mercer Associates re: 2008 Adjusted Funding Target Attainment Percentage (AFTAP) certification for the plan for 2008 and various amendments to the plan, dated 1996 - 2009. Also included is a memo from Terese Coudreaut re: participant fee disclosures. Cambridge Associates reviewed Vanguard's fees for the plan and reported the expense ration was well below industry average. Also Retirement Plan for Employees of The Knight Foundation, Amended and Restated as of January 1, 2008; signed December 10, 2012. A 2nd Amendment to the retirement plan for employees of KF, signed November 14, 2016.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of Knight Foundation, 2000-2002 (Box 2, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 2123
        Retirement Plan for Employees of Knight Foundation, revised and with amendments and IRS Forms. Also includes summary plan descriptions and a 2nd Amendment, dated June 15, 2004 and effective October 1, 2004, to change the interest crediting rate and add joint and survivor annuity options for unmarried participants. Amendments 1st through 5th. A 2nd Amendment, for the retirement plan for employees of the Knight Foundation, effective as of January 1, 2008, as amended and restated ("Plan"), dated November 14, 2016.
      - Correspondence concerning IRS Determination Letter for Knight Foundation Retirement Plan, 2007 March 6-19 (Box 2, Folder 9)
        Knight File Number - 4075
        Letter from IRS requesting additional information and reply from Mercer Human Resource Consulting group. Also includes copies of the plan and its amendments, 2000-2006.
      - KF Retirement Plan Correspondence, 2009 June 22-2010 September 8 (Box 2, Folder 10)
        Knight File Number - 4902
        Northern Trust ERISA Plan disclosure forms for 2009 and 2010; two authorization letters to Mercer re: plan adjustments.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of Knight Foundation - Summary Plan Descriptions -amended and restated, 2008 (Box 2)
        Knight File Number - 5768
        Summary Plan Descriptions amended and restated of the Retirement Plan for Employees of the Knight Foundation on January 1, 2008.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of the Knight Foundation, 2009 (Box 2A, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 5231
        Determination of FAS 87 Expense for the Fiscal Year Ending 12/31/2008 and Actuarial Valuation Report FAS 87 Expense for Fiscal Year Ending 12/31/2009.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of the Knight Foundation, 2010 July (Box 2A, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 5232
        Actuarial Valuation Report FAS 87 Expense for Fiscal Year Ending 12/31/2010.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of the Knight Foundation, 2011 March-September (Box 2A, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 5233
        Actuarial valuation for funding purposes as of 1/1/2010; Actuarial Valuation Report FAS 87 Expense for Fiscal Year Ending 12/31/2011 and Actuarial valuation for funding purposes as of 1/1/2011.
      - Retirement Plan for Employees of the Knight Foundation, 2012 May (Box 2A, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 5543
        Data, assumptions, methods and provisions as of 1/1/2012; actuarial valuation for funding purposes as of 1/1/2012; and actuarial valuation report net periodic benefit cost for fiscal year ending 12/31/2012.
      - Defined Contribution Plan 403(b) 2014, 2014 May 16 (Box 2A, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 5605
        Memo from Terese Coudreaut to 403(b) plan participants disclosing the plan fees as required by Department of Labor regulations.
      - IRS determination letter for pension plan, 2016 January 12 (Box 2A, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 5767
        IRS favorable determination letter for retirement plan, dating 2009 through 2012. This determination letter applies to the amendments dated on 12/10/12 & 12/13/10. It also applies to the amendments dated on 12/07/09 & 03/09/09. IRS letter approved January 12, 2016.
        Restricted - Open in 2026
    - Policies, 1983-2002; 3.2
      - Personnel Policy Manual, 1983 May 1 (Box 2, Folder 11)
        Knight File Number - 2128
        The personnel policy manual spells out specific procedures and provides broad policy guidelines for employee conduct.
      - Policy Manual, 1993 April 1 (Box 3, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 1143
        Knight Foundation employee orientation/policy manual. Includes sections on employment policies, employment classifications, human resources department, harassment, wage and salary policies, performance and salary reviews, benefits, general policies and procedures, standards of conduct, and forms.
      - Policies and Procedures Manual, 2002 March 1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 2376
        Knight Foundation employee orientation/policy manual. Includes sections on introduction to the Foundation, joining the Foundation, employee benefits and compensation, workplace conduct, working at the Foundation, employment classifications, performance and salary reviews, and forms.
    - Staffing, 1990-2017; 3.3
      - Job Descriptions and Advertisements, 1990-2001 (Box 3, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 2129
        Job descriptions and advertisements beginning with the move from Akron to Miami in 1990. These serve to reflect the growth and changes to the organization over the years.
      - Job Descriptions, 1998-2007 (Box 3, Folder 4-5)
        Knight File Number - 4408
        Job descriptions, recruitment ads, and assessment tools for most, but not all, of KF staff positions. Includes, in some cases, job descriptions for several years making it possible to track changes in the positions. (2 folders)
      - Streamlining Committee, 1998 May 12-1999 December 13 (Box 3, Folder 6-7)
        Knight File Number - 2132
        The Streamlining Committee was tasked with improving Knight Foundation operations to allow the staff to work more efficiently and to respond to its constituents in a more timely manner. The Committee identified six desired outcomes and formulated seven recommendations. Included are interim and final reports, an executive summary, memoranda, meeting agendas, proposals from consulting companies and staff evaluations, and process flow charts. Two folders.
      - Knight Foundation Internship Program, 1998-2016 (Box 4, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 3710
        Restricted - Open 2027
        Handbook created when program launched in 1998 includes background, goals and objectives, and description; selection criteria; guidelines; and an implementation plan. Also included is a copy of the updated internship program description, guidelines and sample timesheet (2006) and miscellaneous program-related correspondence. Also included are names and bios of the 2014 and 2016 interns, a thank you note from intern Carolina Wilson and a photo of the interns with Alberto Ibarguen.
      - Performance Management Training, 1999 (Box 4, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 4925
        Workshop materials for supervisory and non-supervisory personnel include performance appraisal preparation, and establishing standards.
      - Candidate Selection Process, 2001 April (Box 4, Folder 3-4)
        Knight File Number - 2130
        Guide prepared by William M. Mercer, Inc. in April 2001 to assist the Knight Foundation in maximizing the interview process for candidates for employment. The guide includes workshop materials, competency models, interview guides, candidate rating forms and interviewing information. Two folders
      - Knowledge Management Initiative: Learning and Support Strategy Taxonomy & Metadata, 2002 November 15-2005 March 1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 4926
        The Knowledge Management Initiative was a strategy for enabling staff to use applications including InterAction and eRoom. Includes memos, minutes, agendas, and presentations.
      - Recruiting and Selection Review and Competency Based Interviewing, 2003 August (Box 4, Folder 6)
        Knight File Number - 4341
        Review of the new selection and recruiting process put into place in 2000. Includes interviews with KF employees and analysis of process. Also included are updates of components of the process: testing and scoring guidelines and competency based interviewing techniques.
      - InterAction Training I and II, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 7)
        Knight File Number - 4927
        Powerpoint slides, instructor's script and training modules.
      - New Employee Orientation/Participant Materials, 2003 (Box 4, Folder 8)
        Knight File Number - 2398
        New Employee Orientation Manual provides information on equipment, procedures, and document management.
      - Performance Management Review, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 1)
        Knight File Number - 4653
        Instructor's Manual, Guide and brochures outlining KF's "Strategy for Renewing the Foundation's System for Managing Performance".
      - New Employee Orientation/Instructor Materials, Version 3.0, 2003 (Box 5, Folder 2)
        Knight File Number - 2399
        New Employee Orientation Manual provides information on equipment, procedures, and document management. The Instructor Manual is the same as the participant manual, except that it also includes instructions on how to facilitate the new employee's use of the manual and how to reinforce learning.
      - New Employee Orientation/Learner Materials, Version 3.51, c. 2004 (Box 5, Folder 3)
        Knight File Number - 4928
      - New Employee Orientation/Instructor Materials, Version 3.51, c. 2004 (Box 5, Folder 4)
        Knight File Number - 4929
      - Transformation Grantmaking Toolkit, 2007 February 20-April 12 (Box 5, Folder 5)
        Knight File Number - 5246